ARGHYA CHATTERJEE



☑ arghyame20buet@gmail.com

https://arghyachatterjee.github.io

https://github.com/ArghyaChatterjee

A robotics and machine learning researcher experienced in applying Deep Learning, Edge & Cloud Computing in Computer Vision for Object Detection, Segmentation & Localization, Advanced Perception based SLAM for Localization, Mapping, Metric & Semantic understanding of the environment, Control theory & Deep Reinforcement Learning for risk aware autonomous robotic exploration in perceptually degraded environments and Swarm Intelligence for multirobot collaboration & rapid exploration in outer space to help take better decision for humans.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

• Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science

Jul 2012 - Aug 2014

GPA: 5.00/5.00

Class Position: 1st/60

Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science Jan 2010 - May 2012 GPA: 5.00/5.00 Class Position: $1^{st}/60$

RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Team Member, Team CoSTAR of NASA JPL

DARPA organized SubT Challenge
Perception Team Leader: Dr. Benjamin Morrell (NASA JPL)
California, USA
Topic: Advanced perception based multi-robot SLAM algorithms efficiency, accuracy & robustness

testing along with object detection & localization capability analysis for robots like Spot, Husky & Roller-copter with NeBula autonomy setup (built by Team CoSTAR) mounted.

Team Supervisor & Educator, STEMX 365

JAXA (& NASA) org. Kibo-Astrobee ISS Robot Programming Challenge
International Project Coordinator: Mizanul H. Chowdhury (MIT)
Tokyo, Japan
Topic: Autonomously operate Astrobee (A free flying robot) inside ISS avoiding obstacles with 3D perception, following way points and detecting QR & AR Tag.

• Research Assistant at Mars Rover Lab (MRL), BUET

Project Researcher, Advisor & Instructor for URC, ERC & KRPC

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Ashiqur Rahman (BUET)

Topic: Autonomous Navigation Based on GPS, SLAM & Object Detection and Plan Path accordingly for Safe Exploration of Rovers on Rough Terrains, Caves and Mineral Ores of Earth and Mars.

• Software Team Leader & Member, Team Interplanetar

ESA organized ERC & Mars Society organized URC

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Ashiqur Rahman (BUET)

Topic: GPS Based Autonomous Mars Rover Navigation & On-board Object Detection for URC and Way-point Based Autonomous Mars Rover Navigation & On-board AR Tag Detection for ERC.

• Researcher & Collaborator at Department of ME, BUET

Undergraduate Thesis

Mar 2018 – Apr 2019
Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur (BUET) and Dr. Muhammad Abir (MIT)

Dhaka, Bangladesh
Topic: Computational Investigation on Pool Boiling IR Images for Segmentation of Dry Spots
Automatically and Evaluating Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural
Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

• Team Leader, Team Octatron

Undergraduate Project
Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib (BUET)
Mar 2017 - Feb 2018
Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib (BUET)
Topic: Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings and Areas, and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

• Researcher & Technical Leader, Team Out of the Box

Microsoft BD Internship Project Jan 2017 - May 2017
Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman (Microsoft) Dhaka, Bangladesh
Topic: Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Through Mobile Application Using

Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

• Team Leader, Team Igniters

Undergraduate Project Jul 2016 - Feb 2017 Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam (BUET) Dhaka, Bangladesh Topic: Hand Wearable Solar Powered Obstacle Detection and Safe Navigation Device for Blind

People in Low Cost.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team
Teaching Assistant at Mars Rover Lab (MRL), BUET

• JAXA org. Kibo Astrobee ISS Robot Prog. Challenge Educator & Instructor of Teams from Bangladesh, STEMX 365

• National Space Carnival & Camp Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps

• Bangladesh Astronomical Society Instructor for Workshops & Seminars Oct 2020 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan 2020 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh Sep 2019 - Jun 2020 Dhaka, Bangladesh

Mar 2017 – Apr 2019 Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration (BARC)

Advisor & Fellow Member

Jan 2020 – Present

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Activities: Give advice on research activities & how the organization should operate.

Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization)
 Head of STEM Education & Development
 Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in

Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education in Bangladesh.

• American Astronomical Society
Country Collaborator & Member
Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh and Reported to Proper

AAS Authority for Publishing on their Magazines.

PUBLICATIONS

- Matteo Palieri, Benjamin Morrell, Abhishek Thakur, Kamak Ebadi, Jeremy Nash, Arghya Chatterjee, Christoforos Kanellakis, Luca Carlone, Cataldo Guaragnella, Ali-akbar Aghamohammadi, "LOCUS: A Multi-Sensor Lidar-Centric Solution for High-Precision Odometry and 3D Mapping in Real-Time," IEEE Robotics & Automation Letters Journal, 2020, vol: 6/2, pp. 421-428.
- Arghya Chatterjee, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," 2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI), Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- Arghya Chatterjee, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," Proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS), Dhaka, 2017.

INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS

• Microsoft Bangladesh Limited
Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products

• Khulna Power Company Limited
Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks)

Jan 2017 - May 2017 Dhaka, Bangladesh Oct 2018 – Oct 2018 Khulna, Bangladesh

SKILL SETS

- Prg. Language: Python, C++, C#, C, R, Arduino, Java, Java S, HTML, PHP, CSS, & LATEX.
- Framework & OS: ROS, OpenCV, PCL, Nvidia Isaac SDK, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Caffe, CUDA, OpenGL, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, Linux, Mac, Windows & Android.
- **Software & Tool:** Git, Github, Gitlab, Docker, MIPAR, Solidworks, Ansys, PLC, Blender, Unity & UE 4, Verge3D, Carla Simulator, Microsoft Airsim, Deeplab, OpenPose3D, Meshroom, Meshlab, CloudCompare, Open3D, OpenDroneMap, OpenSpace, Photoshop, Kdenlive & MS Office Family.
- **IDE, Compiler & Text Editor:** CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Android Studio, Nodejs, IntelliJ IDEA, VS Code & Notepad++.
- Cloud Platform: AWS Compute, AWS RoboMaker & Storage, GCP, Google Colab.
- Hardware: GPS (RTK), IMU, VLP-16 (3D) & RPLidar (2D) LIDAR, Intel Realsense D200 & 400 series RGBD & L515 Lidar Camera, ZED 3D Camera, Microsoft Kinect Camera, Nvidia Jetson & Intel NUC Boards, Arduino & Raspberry PI Boards, Pixhawk, Ardupilot, VESC, BLDC motor, Nvidia AMD GTX Boards & Oculus Rift S VR Headset.
- Robotic Platforms: Husky (custom developed autonomy setup mounted) from Clearpath Robotics, Spot (custom developed autonomy setup mounted) from Boston Dynamics, ANYmal from ANYbotics, Astrobee from NASA, Mongol-E v4 (custom developed robot with arm) from Team Interplanetar, Octacopter (custom developed UAV) from Team Octatron.
- **Technology:** Computer Vision, Image Proc., ML, DL, DRL, Object Detection & Localization, Image Segmentation, Action Recognition, Pose Tracking, SLAM, Path Planning, Control, Photogrammetry, 3D Printing, AR, VR & MR, Game Dev, Web Dev, Video Editing, GPU, Edge & Cloud Computing.
- Language Proficiency: Bangla, English & Hindi.

AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

•	Special Grant from ICT Division (Ministry) of Bangla	adesh	Feb 2020
	Awarded to BUET Mars Rover Lab (MRL) for outstanding		Dhaka, BD
•	Gold Medalist from Duke of Edinburgh International		Dec 2019
	Awarded for Outstanding Extra-curricular & Service to t		London, UK
•	2nd in Asia & 16th Internationally in European Mars		Sep 2019
	Organized by European Space Foundation (ESF) & Europ	pean Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, Poland
•	Special Fund & Grant from BUET Alumni Associatio	n Trust	Jul 2019
	Awarded to Team Interplanetar of BUET MRL for compe	tition & robotics research	Dhaka, BD
•	Finalist in IEEE SS12 International Project Competit	tion & Maker Fair	Jul 2017
	Organized at SS12: Age of Innovation and Maker Fair 20	17	Hyderabad, India
•	1st in National Project Show Competition (Senior Ca	ategory)	May 2017
	Organized at EEE Day, BUET		Dhaka, BD
•	3rd in Inter University Project Show Competition		Apr 2017
	Organized at Mechanical Festival, BUET		Dhaka, BD
•	1st in National Poster Presentation Competition		Mar 2017
	Organized at Robolution, MIST		Dhaka, BD
•	2nd in Inter University Project Show Competition		Nov 2016
	Organized at CSE Day, BUET		Dhaka, BD
•	1st in All Classes (2002 - 2014)		
	• Primary at Elizabeth M Primary School (2002-2006) • Junior at Khulna BKS School (2006-2009)		
	• Secondary at Khulna BKS School (2009-2012)	H. S. at Khulna Public Co	llege (2013-2014)
•	Govt. Merit Scholarship from Education Board of Bangladesh (2006 - 2019)		
	 Primary Scholarship (2006-2009) Junior Scholarship (2010-2012) 		-2012)
	• Secondary Scholarship (2013-2014) • H. Secondary Scholarship		(2015-2019)
•	Olympiad Achievements		
	• 1 st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14 • 1 st in Reg. R. of Zoology Olympiad'1		Olympiad'14
	• 3 rd in Reg. & 10 th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13	3 rd in Reg. R. of Math Oly	ympiad'14

CERTIFICATIONS (COURSERA)

• Machine Learning by Stanford University, Feb 2018.

- **Deep Learning Specialization** (5 course) by Deeplearning.ai, Sept 2018.
- Modern Robotics: Mechanics, Planning & Control Specialization by Northwestern Uni, May 2021.
- **Control of Mobile Robots** by Georgia Institute of Technology, May 2020.
- Image & Video Processing by Duke University, Nov 2018.
- Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines Télécom, May 2019.
- Wireless Communications for Everybody by Yonsei University, Dec 2018.
- AstroTech by University of Edinburgh, Dec 2019.

LEADERSHIPS

• **Head** of STEM Education & Development

• Software Team Lead

• Technical Lead of Internship Project

• **President** (Senior Rover Mate)

President

• **Team Lead** for Development & Planning

Youthprenuer Network Team Interplanetar, BUET Microsoft BD BUET Rover Scout Group

Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET

ESAB, BUET Unit

VOLUNTEERING

• **Sceptre (Poverty Alleviation Organization)** Jan 2015 - Present Activities: Org. free medical camps & distribute dress & sewing machines to poor people monthly.

• **BUET Rover Scout Group** Feb 2015 - Apr 2019 Activities: Volunteered on tree plantation camp & org. flood relief distribution camp monthly.

• Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on medical camps, tree plantation events & sports day at KBKSS.

WORKSHOPS & SEMINARS

- International Youth Leadership Summit-2016 org. by BYLC.
- 4 th BIRDS International Workshop on Demystifying Satellites org. by BRAC University.
- Seminar on **Zero Robotics** by M.H. Chowdhury of MIT org. by Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET.
- Seminar on **Space Stories and ISS Experiences** by Astronaut Dr. Tess Caswell of NASA org. by Dept. of Civil Eng., BUET.
- Seminar on **4-fold Resolution Increase in Endoscopic Imaging** by J.M. Kahn of Stanford University org. by Dept. of Biomedical Eng., BUET.
- Workshop on ML, PCB, Graphic Designing, & Technical Paper Writing org. by IEEE BDS.
- Workshop on **CFD**, **Ansys Fluent**, **Solidworks & 3D Printing** org. by Involute Tech BD.

MEMBERSHIPS

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Eng. (**IEEE**)
- American Institute of Aero and Astronautics (AIAA) •
- Bangladesh Astronomy Research Collaboration
- American Astronomical Society (AAS)
- IEEE Robotics and Automation Society
- Bangladeshi Researchers Network

REFERENCES

• Dr. Benjamin Morrell

Perception Team Leader, Team CoSTAR Ex. Post Doc Researcher, JPL, Caltech. Robotics Technologist, NASA JPL. Email: benjamin.morrell@jpl.nasa.gov

• Dr. Md. Ashiqur Rahman

Project Supervisor Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Email: ashiqurrahman@me.buet.ac.bd • Dr. Muhammad Abir

Thesis Co-Supervisor
Ex. Post Doc. Researcher, Dept. of NSE, MIT.
Imaging Specialist, Phoenix Nuclear Labs.
Email: miabir@mit.edu

• Mizanul H. Chowdhury

Project Supervisor Admin of ZR, Space Systems Lab, MIT. Email: mizanul@mit.edu